Lewis M. Haupt Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Lewis M. Haupt Papers 1849-1923 (bulk 1892-1903)
MSS25296
Haupt, Lewis M. (Lewis Muhlenberg), b. 1844
3,000 items
9 containers
4.0 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Civil engineer and public official. Correspondence, minutes, memoranda, reports, speeches, and articles relating to the selection of a route for an isthmian canal and to Haupt's efforts to secure the Nicaraguan route includes records of the Nicaraguan Canal Commission and the Isthmian Canal Commission, with further material relating to Herman Haupt and his duties as chief of construction and operation of the United States Bureau of Military Railroads during the Civil War.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937--Correspondence.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925--Correspondence.; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919--Correspondence.; Haupt, Herman, 1817-1905. Herman Haupt letterbook. 1861-1863.; Haupt, Lewis M. (Lewis Muhlenberg), 1844-1937.; Hay, John, 1838-1905--Correspondence.; Morgan, John Tyler, 1824-1907--Correspondence.; Search, Theodore C.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Isthmian Canal Commission (U.S.) Isthmian Canal Commission (U.S.) records.; Nicaraguan Canal Commission (U.S.) Nicaraguan Canal Commission (U.S.) records.; United States. Bureau of Military Railroads.
Subjects
Canals--Nicaragua.; Military railroads.
Occupations
Civil engineers.; Public officials--Pennsylvania.
Provenance
The papers of Lewis M. Haupt, civil engineer and public official, were purchased by the Library of Congress, 1930-1938.
Additional Guides
The Lewis M. Haupt Papers are mentioned in Report of the Librarian of Congress, 1930, p. 77. A list of the major correspondents along with the dates of their letters is kept in the Manuscript Division Reading Room with the finding aid.
Related Material
A related collection in the Manuscript Division is the John Tyler Morgan Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Lewis M. Haupt are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1844, Mar. 21 Born, Gettysburg, Pa.
1863 1867 Cadet, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1867 1869 Engineer, United States Army
1869 1872 Topographical engineer, Fairmount Park, Philadelphia, Pa.
1872 1892 Professor of civil engineering, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa.
1873 Married Isabella Christina Cromwell
1892 1937 Private engineering practice, Philadelphia, Pa.
1897 1899 Member, Nicaraguan Canal Commission
1899 1902 Member, Isthmian Canal Commission
1904 Won gold and silver medals for engineering feats, St. Louis Exposition, St. Louis, Mo.
1911 Patented automatic device for reclaiming eroded beaches
1937, Mar. 10 Died, Bala Cynwyd, Pa.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Lewis Muhlenberg Haupt (1844-1937) span the years, 1849-1923, with the bulk of the items dating from 1892 to 1903. A majority of the collection concerns Haupt’s work for the Nicaraguan Canal Commission and the Isthmian Canal Commission and his attempts to secure the Nicaraguan Canal. The papers are in English and are organized into the following series: Family Papers, Correspondence, Records of the Nicaraguan and the Isthmian Canal Commissions, and Miscellany.
The Correspondence deals exclusively with the canal question. Haupt was an advocate of the Nicaraguan route rather than the Panamanian, and lobbied for the former. Correspondence about his lobbying efforts are found in his letters to Senator John Tyler Morgan, the Senate advocate of the Nicaraguan route, and Theodore C. Search, president of the National Association of Manufacturers. The letters are arranged chronologically with an indexed letterbook for 1900 at the end of the correspondence.
The Records of the Nicaraguan and the Isthmian Canal Commissions contain minutes of commission meetings; internal memoranda; questionnaires; memorials sent to the commission; working papers; drawings and charts; newspaper clippings; congressional hearings, speeches, and proposed bills; and reports submitted to and prepared by the commission, including Preliminary Report of the Isthmian Canal Commission and drafts of the final report. The working papers consist of articles and statistical and climatological data on Central America; information on sizes, drafts, and weights of ships; and shipping rates. The internal memoranda are conjectural papers written for the commission by its members on the cost of building the canal, projected income and profits, and expected usage. The drawings and charts contain Haupt’s projection of the Nicaraguan route and a map of the route printed in a contemporary journal.
The Miscellany file includes speeches and articles by Haupt supporting the canal route through Nicaragua and advertisements for his classes at the Franklin Institute in Philadelphia.
The Family Papers consist of typescripts of letters written by Haupt's father, Herman Haupt, between July 1861 and September 1862, a letterbook of Herman Haupt’s correspondence from November 1862 to August 1863, and a letter from Haupt to his son Lewis M. Haupt in September 1863. These letters contain a large amount of family correspondence as well as official correspondence concerning Herman Haupt’s duties as chief of construction and operation of the United States Bureau of Military Railroads during the Civil War.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
Family Papers, 1861-1863
Correspondence, 1890-1923
Records of the Nicaraguan and the Isthmian Canal Commissions, 1849-1904
Miscellany, 1895-1905
Container List
- Family Papers, 1861-1863 (Box 1)
  Typescripts of Herman Haupt’s letters, a letterbook with index, and a letter to Lewis M. Haupt.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Letters of Herman Haupt, typescripts, July 1861-Sept. 1862 (Box 1)
  - Letterbook of Herman Haupt, Nov. 1862-Aug. 1863 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Herman Haupt to Lewis M. Haupt, 1863 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1890-1923 (Box 2-3)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent relating to the isthmian canal.
  Arranged chronologically with a letterbook from 1900 at the end.
  - 1890-1900 (Box 2)
  - 1901-1923, undated, (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - Letterbook, 1900 (Box 3)
- Records of the Nicaraguan and the Isthmian Canal Commissions, 1849-1904 (Box 4-8)
  Minutes, internal memoranda, questionnaires, working papers, memorials, reports, drawings, charts, newspaper clippings, and congressional hearings and speeches.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Internal memoranda, 1893-1904, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Memorials to the commission, 1898-1903 (Box 4)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1899-1902, undated (Box 4)
  - Questionnaires sent by the commission, 1899 (Box 4)
  - Drawings and charts, circa 1887 (Box 5)
  - Working papers, 1849, 1892-1902, (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Congressional hearings, speeches, and documents, 1892-1901 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1898-circa 1903 (Box 6)
  - Reports, undated, (3 folders); (4 folders) (Box 6, Box 7)
  - Preliminary Report of the Isthmian Canal Commission, 1900 (Box 8)
  - Final report, drafts, circa 1901, (4 folders) (Box 8)
- Miscellany, 1895-1905 (Box 9)
  Advertisements, articles, and speeches.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Advertisements for classes at Franklin Institute, Philadelphia, Pa., 1898-1901 (Box 9)
  - Articles, circa 1895-1905 (Box 9)
  - Speeches, 1902-1905 (Box 9)